A Finding Aid to the Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau Papers, 1853-1977, bulk 1864-1920, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bougeliz
Archives of American Art
Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau papers
1853-1977
AAA.bougeliz
Archives of American Art
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of painter Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1853 to 1977, with the bulk of the material dating from 1864 to 1920. Found within the papers are correspondence written to Bouguereau's immediate family; clippings and miscellaneous printed material; and photographs of Bouguereau and her husband Adolphe.
Also in the Archives are papers lent for microfilming on reel 3135 and returned to Bouguereau's grandniece, Miriam Dunnan. These papers are not described in the container listing of this finding aid and are available only on microfilm. Included are photographs of Elizabeth and Adolphe Bouguereau and Imogene Robinson Morrell.
Gardner, Elizabeth Jane, 1837-1922
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau papers were donated between 1983 and 1986 by Bouguereau's grandniece, Miriam Gardner Dunnan.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 3464 and 3967 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau (1837-1922) lived and worked in Paris, France. Bouguereau was born in Exeter, New Hampshire, graduated from the Lasell Female Seminary in Auburndale, Massachusetts, in 1856, and taught French at the Worcester School of Design and Fine Arts. In the summer of 1864, she travelled to Paris with a former art instructor, Imogene Robinson, with the intention of furthering her art studies. Upon arrival, they copied paintings at the Luxembourg Museum and Bouguereau studied in a number of studios, including the studio of Jean-Baptiste Tissier, a cooperative women's studio, and the École Jardin des Plantes. In 1868, she gained entry to the Paris Salon, one of only six women invited to participate before 1870.
Bouguereau painted in the academic French style, which depicted popular subjects such as country life, biblical scenes, and children and animals. In 1973, she gained entry to the acclaimed Académie Julian, where her instructors included Jules-Joseph Lefebvre and Adolphe William Bouguereau, whom she would later marry in 1896. Bouguereau was the first American woman to be awarded a medal by the Salon, winning a bronze medal in 1887 for The Farmer's Daughter. She also won medals at the 1876 Philadelphia Centennial Exhibition and the 1889 Paris Universal Exposition. After her marriage to Adolphe Bouguereau, she ceased painting to care for her husband and resumed only after his death in 1905. She continued to produce works until 1914, when her failing eyesight forced her to stop, and died in her country home in St. Cloud, France in 1922.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1853 to 1977, with the bulk of the material dating from 1864 to 1920. Found within the papers are correspondence written to Bouguereau's immediate family; clippings and miscellaneous printed material; and photographs of Bouguereau and her husband Adolphe.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Series 1: Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau papers, 1853-1977 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Bouguereau, William Adolphe, 1825-1905; Painters--France--Paris; Painting, Modern--19th century--France--Paris; Photographs; Women painters--France
- Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau Papers, 1853-1977; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The papers of painter Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau consist of correspondence written by Bouguereau to her immediate family, including her mother, Jane Lowell Gardner, her sister, Maria (Ria) P. Gardner, her brother, John Edward Gardner, her sister-in-law, Miriam Gardner, and her nephews, Perley and John Jr. In these letters, Bougureau covers topics ranging from the progress of her work to life in France, European travels, updates on friends and family, and commentary on contemporary historical and political events. The papers also include copies of clippings, an invitation, an exhibition announcement, and photographs of Bouguereau and her husband Adolphe.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are minimally arranged by document type.
  - Correspondence, Bouguereau, Elizabeth Gardner, circa 1885-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, Jane Lowell (mother), 1866, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, Maria "Ria" P. (sister), 1865-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, John Edward (brother), 1864-1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, Miriam (sister in law), 1878-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, Perley (nephew), 1881-1920 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, Gardner, John (nephew), 1888-1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings, Article and Poem, circa 1885-1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Printed Material, Invitation, Exhibition Announcement, and Clippings, 1896-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Elizabeth Gardner Bouguereau, circa 1858-1911 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photograph of Elizabeth and Adolphe Bouguereau, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 16)